Guide to the Graham Arthur Barden Papers, 1934-1960
Graham Arthur Barden papers 1934-1960
Barden, Graham Arthur, 1896-1967
185 Linear feet 370 Boxes
Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Barden Papers were presented to the Rubenstein Library in 1961 and 1965 by Representative Barden.
Biographical Note
1896 Born, Sept. 25, in Turkey Township, Sampson County, N. C.
1920 Graduated from University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
1921 Practiced law, New Bern, N. C., in firm of Whitehurst & Barden. Appointed Judge of Craven County, Re-elected three times
1922 Married Agnes Foy. Later had two children, Agnes and Graham Arthur, Jr,
1930 Practiced law in firm of Barden & Stith
1932-33 Elected to N. C. General Assembly from Craven County
1934 Elected to U. S. House of Representatives from N. C. Third District, Served continuously until retirement
1950 Became Chairman, Education and Labor Committee, Held chairmanship during Democratic majority sessions
1960 Retired in New Bern, N. C,
1967 Died, Jan. 29, New Bern. N. C.
Committee Membership
74th Congress 1935-36: Education; Library; Rivers & Harbors; Special Committee to Investigate Campaign Expenditures
75th Congress 1937-38: Education; Library; Patents; Rivers & Harbors (Left Patents Committee and placed on Labor Committee during this Congress)
76th Congress 1939-40: Education; Labor; Library; Rivers & Harbors
77th Congress 1941-42: Census; Education; Labor; Library; Rivers & Harbors
78th Congress 1943-44: Census; Education (Chairman; Civil Service; Labor, Library; Rivers & Harbors; Special Committee to Investigate Campaign Expenditures
79th Congress 1945-46: Census; Civil Service; Education (Chairman); Expenditures in the Executive Departments; Labor; Library; Rivers & Harbors
80th-86th Congresses 1947-60: Education and Labor Chairman 1951-52 and 1955-60
Collection Overview
The Graham Arthur Barden Papers consist of the office files of Democratic Congressman Barden from his first election to Congress in 1934 through his retirement in 1960. Correspondence, public statements, and miscellaneous Items relate to his service as a member and then chairman of the House Committee on Education and Labor. His interest in matters concerning his constituents in the Third District of North Carolina is reflected throughout the collection.
Congressman Barden left his successor, Congressman David Newton Henderson, many papers about ongoing business, especially local projects. These papers came to the library in the Henderson Papers where they are filed, Consult the Inventory of the David N. Henderson Papers for this material that dates prior to 1961 when Henderson took office. The Barden material dates as early as 1930.
The Graham Arthur Barden Papers span Barden's political career from 1933 through his retirement in 1960. There is little material for 1933-1934. Scattered Items pertain to Barden's work in the North Carolina General Assembly and papers for 1934 deal chiefly with his successful campaign in North Carolina's Third Congressional District for the United States Congress. The papers from 1935 through 1960 form a comprehensive record of Barden's congressional activities. To facilitate the use of the collection, the Barden Papers have been arranged in the following series:
I. Subject Files
II. Education and labor
III General Legislation
IV. Correspondence
V. Personal
For more detailed information on the arrangement and content of each series, refer to the Series Descriptions and Container Listing which follow.
The Barden Papers consist in part of correspondence exchanged between Barden and other committee members, legislators, and officials of government agencies. Educators, labor leaders, businessmen, and prominent North Carolinians also communicated with Barden. A large category contains numerous letters from constituents in the Third District of North Carolina who wrote concerning local projects, employment prospects, veteran's benefits, and issues immediately affecting them. There is also a Quantity of "pressure mail" urging Barden to support or oppose certain legislation. Although this type of correspondence is often short and repetitive, it represents a broad geographical area outside of Barden's district and include letters providing comment ranging from the highly articulate to the semi-literate on issues of the day
In addition to correspondence, the Barden Papers contain typescripts and drafts of speeches, legal briefs, and reports. There is also printed material related to the development of various bills, including reports, hearings and confidential committee prints. Many such Items are public documents and have been retained because of the legislative history they reveal, because they have immediate relation to the collection, or because they contain corrections or marginalia written by Barden. Other government documents, however, such as final or complete copies of committee hearings and reports or documents sent to Barden as a courtesy, have been removed since they pertain only tangentially to the collection. A researcher may therefore wish to consult appropriate printed government documents located elsewhere in the Perkins Library.
Many printed Items that Barden collected for research for committee work or accumulated for general information have also been retained. Labor, education, and other partisan groups furnished many of these Items. The papers also contain clippings and some photographs, mainly of Seymour Johnson Air Force Base and Goldsboro, North Carolina.
As a whole, the Barden Collection illustrates legislative trends, particularly in education and labor, from the Depression to the Kennedy years, and the role that Barden played as a member and chairman of an important House Committee. Major issues include federal aid to education, labor-management relations, labor standards, and minimum wage legislation,
Coverage for legislation considered by committees other than Education and Labor is uneven and is likely to reflect Barden's own interests or viewpoints. Since Barden continually tried to serve his constituents, for example agriculture information is more abundant than foreign policy material. The Third District was largely rural, and agriculture, fishing, and related industries were important to the District, as were lumbering, preliminary processing of tobacco, and some furniture manufacturing. Barden was also instrumental in the establishment and development of several military installations in his district, including Camp Lejeune Marine Base and Seymour Johnson Air Force Base. These activities, as well as other issues of national importance, are reflected in the materials filed under General Legislation and in the Third District Projects and Constituent Concerns files.
Since Barden was consistently unopposed in congressional elections there is little campaign material, Family and exclusively personal material is also rare.
A note on Processing: The five series roughly parallel the arrangement of the tiles as they came from Barden's office, with some consolidation of smaller units, particularly in Series I, the Subject Series.
Certain Items or groups of material were not retained. These include duplicates standard and repetitive responses to pressure mail, and ephemeral material or papers pertaining to ordinary facilitative processes.
Samples from other categories were retained on the following basis:
1. Veteran's files - "C" names retained
2. Employment files - "C" names retained
3. Service Academy Appointments - General files and "C" names retained
4. Post Office - Morehead City files and files for county seats in district retained
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
United States.--Congress.--House
Education -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Labor and laboring classes -- United States -- History -- 20th century
Camp Lejeune (N.C.)
Seymour Johnson Air Force Base (Goldsboro, N.C.)
Veterans
Tobacco industry -- North Carolina
Furniture industry and trade -- North Carolina
North Carolina -- Politics and government
Military bases -- North Carolina
Contents of Collection
- Subject Series
  - A. Third District Projects and Constituent Concerns
    - Agriculture, 1940-1959 (Box 1, Folder 1-5)
      Material deals with general agricultural matters rather than specific crops, Much of the correspondence concerns Department of Agriculture regulations. Various Departmental reports are included.
    - Air Force, 1950-1960 (Folder 6)
    - Air Force Academy, 1950-1954
    - Airports, ca. 1939-1943, 1951-1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Early correspondence concerns the location of Army airports for national defense, Later material deals with Federal Aeronautics Administration allocations to North Carolina, rumors of airports to be built in Barden's district by the Civil Aeronautics Authority, and proposed air service to the district by national airlines.
    - Alliance School Dredging Project, 1948
    - Allotments, 1941-1946, 1951-1958 (Folder 8-12, Box 3, Folder 13-16)
      Correspondence revolves around Barden's attempts to assist wives and relatives of soldiers of the Third District in getting monthly allotments from the soldiers and the Federal government.
    - Ambassador to the Vatican, Appointment of, 1951-1952 (Folder 17)
    - American Legion, ca. 1937-1951 (Folder 17-18)
    - Ancestors ca. 1955-1960 (Folder 18)
      Material refers to Barden's ancestry.
    - Arapahoe Community Building Project, 1934-1938
    - Armories - State Projects, 1935-1936
    - Army, ca. 1943-1960 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Article in U. S. A., 1953 (Folder 20)
      This folder contains a copy of Barden's article, Our Unsolved Labor Problems, which appeared in U. S. A., February, 1953, and letters thanking him for complimentary copies sent to friends and colleagues.
    - Atlantic Ball Park Project, 1937 (Folder 21)
    - Atlantic Dredging Project, 1935-1940
    - Atlantic School Project, 1936
    - Atomic Energy Commission, 1950 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Bachelor School Project, 1938 (Folder 22)
    - Banks, 1953, 1958
    - Bayboro Court House Project, 1936-1939
    - Beach Erosion Project, 1935-1936 (Folder 22-23)
      Most of this correspondence deals with patronage on the beach erosion project.
    - Bear Creek Project, 1940 (Folder 23)
    - Bear Inlet Project [1940]
    - Beaufort Airport Project, 1942-1944
    - Beaufort Community Building Project, 1935
    - Beaufort Dock Project, 1938-1939 (Folder 24)
    - Beaufort Federal Building Project, 1935-1937
    - Beaufort Gymnasium Project, 1935-1936
    - Beaufort Hospital Project, 1938
    - Beaufort Lunch Room and Cannery Project, 1944
    - Beaufort Radio Station, 1954
    - Beaufort Recreation and Curb Market Project, 1940-1943
    - Beaufort School Project, 1945-1946 (Box 5, Folder 25)
    - Berlin Situation, 1959
    - Bogue Inlet Coast Guard Station, 1938-1939
    - Brinson Memorial School Dormitory Project, 1938
    - Browns Creek Project, 1935
    - Buck Swamp Drainage Project, 1935
    - Burgaw, Town of, 1952-1957
    - Burgaw Sewer Project, 1936
    - Burgaw Streets Project, 1938
    - Cabbage, 1945 (Folder 26)
    - Calico Creek Project, 1938-1939
    - Calypso, Town of, 1954-1955
    - Camp Lejeune High School Project, 1959
    - Cape Fear River Project, 1935 - 39
    - Carolina Beach Inlet Project, 1949
    - Cartaret Rural Electrification Administration, 1940-1941 (Folder 27)
    - Cartaret County School Project, 1936-1937
    - Cartaret County Sewing Room Project 1937-1939
    - Cartaret County Streets--Beaufort, 1938
    - Casualties, World War II, 1941-1946 (Folder 28-30)
      Correspondence concerning Barden's efforts to help his constituents determine whether or not family and friends in the Armed Forces were alive.
    - Catherine Lake Project 1940 (Box 6, Folder 31)
    - Cedar Creek at Sealevel Project, 1937see also, Glovers Creek
    - Census, ca. 1937-1959 (Folder 31-32)
    - Census, Business, 1935-1936, 1948-1950 (Folder 32)
    - Census, Farm, 1934-1935, 1944-1945 (Folder 33)
    - Cherry Blossom Festival, 1956-1957 (Box 6, Folder 33)
    - Churches (U. S.) in Foreign Countries, 1954
      Material refers to the closing of Protestant churches in Italy (Church of Christ) and Spain (Southern Baptist Mission).
    - Churches, Property For, 1954
      Information concerns the attempts by several Third District churches to rent or buy U. S. military base land for their use.
    - Civil Aeronautics Administration, 1956-1958
      This section includes a Raleigh-Durham Airport brief presented to the Civil Aeronautics Board in 1958 and information relating to airport projects under the Airport Program of the CAA.
    - Civil Defense, 1956-1958 (Folder 34)
      Included are reports of the North Carolina Council on Civil Defense.
    - Civil Service Commission, ca. 1940-1959
      This segment contains a May, 1944, report by the CSC on the militarization of the Women's Air Force Service Pilots (WASPS)
    - Civilian Conservation Corps, 1935-1940 (Folder 34-35)
    - Clinton, Town of, 1955-1959 (Folder 36)
    - Clinton Chamber of Commerce, 1946
    - Clinton Hospital Project, 1938-1943
    - Clinton School, 1938
    - Clinton Sewage Facilities Project, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 37)
    - Clinton Streets Project, 1938
    - Clinton Tobacco Market, 1945-1948
    - Coal, 1945-1946, 1953 (Folder 37-38)
      Most of the correspondence deals with coal shortages and Barden's efforts to increase the quotas of towns in his district.
    - Coast Guard, 1934-1959 (Folder 38-42, Box 8, Folder 43-44)
      Correspondence relates mainly to Barden's attempts to assist Third District members of the Coast Guard in obtaining transfers to the North Carolina area. Other information of a more general nature on the Coast Guard is also contained in these folders.
    - Coastal Plain Experiment Station, 1935-1940 (Folder 45)
    - Coconut Oil, 1959 (Folder 46)
    - Commerce, Department of, ca. 1946-1960
    - Commissions, 1950-1951
    - Communism, 1956 (Folder 47)
    - Confederate Monuments, 1935, 1939
      Material concerns the erection of memorials to Confederate soldiers and Robert E. Lee at Arlington National Cemetery.
    - Confederate Widows, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 47)
    - Contracts, 1950-1952
      Much of this material deals with Federal government contracts
    - Corn, 1948
    - Corn-Hog Section, Agricultural Adjustment
    - Administration, 1935-1936
    - Cotton, 1949-1960 (Folder 48)
    - Courtesy, 1959-1960
    - Cove City Community Building Project, 1936 (Folder 49)
    - Cove City Drainage Project 1938
    - Cove City School Project, 1940
    - Crackpots, 1953-1960 (Folder 50-51)
      Letters from people Barden considered crackpots.
    - Craven County Forestry Project, 1939 (Folder 52)
    - Craven County Sanitary Project, 1938
    - Croatan National Forest Youth Camp Site, 1939-1940, 1948
      Early correspondence deals with the location of the camp, and the establishment of a white camp before a colored one; later correspondence focuses on the attempt to complete the project which was interrupted by the war.
    - Croatan School Project, 1938-1939
    - Cuba, 1952
    - Customs Houses, 1936
    - Davis Harbor Project, 1939
    - Defense, Department of, 1959-1960 (Folder 52-53)
      Bulk of material on new directives by the Department concerning the movement of household goods of servicemen, and the awarding of that business to moving companies. Also includes correspondence on other defense contracts.
    - Demobilization and Discharge Regulations, 1945 (Folder 53)
    - Democratic Party, National and State, 1935-1939, 1946-1947, 1955-1960 (Folder 53-55)
      Early material includes information on finances, the activities of the Democratic National Committee Women's Division, and a report of The Cooperative Committee for 1936-1937. Material of 1940 's concerns the meeting of the Democratic Caucus of the 80th Congress. Later material concerns both national and state matters. National matters include: statements by the Democratic Advisory Council on important issues, Democratic Fact Sheet on Eisenhower-Nixon fiscal policy, and much material on 1960 Presidential Campaign (both nomination and election).
    - (Box 9, Folder 53-55)
      State material deals with the activities of the N. C. Democratic Club of Washington, fund raising, and getting out the Democratic vote.
    - Direct Loans, 1951-1959 (Box 10, Folder 56-58)
      Most material concerns Veterans Administration loans and policy statements; a few Small Business Administration loans.
    - Dolls Creek Project 1937-1940, 1944 (Folder 59)
    - Dover Community Building Project, 1938
    - Duplin County Community Buildings and School, 1935-1938
    - Duplin County Sewing Room, 1938
    - Duplin County Teacherage and Auditorium, 1939
    - East Carolina Cooperative Exchange, 1936 (Folder 60)
    - East Carolina Regional Housing Authority, ca. 1941-1952 (Folder 60-61)
    - Economic Stabilization, Office of, 1951 (Folder 61)
    - Education, North Carolina Department of, 1958
    - Employees' Compensation Commission, 1934-1939 (Box 11, Folder 62)
    - Employment Security--U. S. & N. C., ca. 1946-1954
    - Factory Landing Project, 1936-1937
    - Faison Cold Storage Project, 1938
    - Farm Security Administration, ca. 1938-1945 (Folder 63)
      Most material deals with FSA statistics and constituents' problems with the FSA. 1943 investigative report of FSA by Rep. Harold Cooley.
    - Farm Security Administration--Appointments
    - Lists, 1935-1941
    - Farmers Home Administration, ca. 1951-1957
    - Federal Communications Commission, 1941-1960 (Folder 64-66)
      Most material focuses on applications for radio and television station permits. 1954-1957 contains material on the Channel 5 controversy between WRAL and WPTF.
    - Federal Housing Administration, 1935-1940 (Folder 67)
    - (Box 12, Folder 68)
      Pamphlet (24pp.) on architectural modernization; pamphlet (24pp.) on How to Have the Home You Want. 1939 - information on the investigation of the FHA in N. C.; Barden's views on the FHA. Statistics on FHA loans in N. C. March, 1940 - letter to Barden about Charles Laban Abernethy.
    - Federal Land Bank, 1936 (Folder 68)
    - Federal Power Commission, 1960
      One case involves the need in Shelby, N. C., for more natural gas from Transcontinental Gas Pipe Line Corp. through the FPC
    - Federal Trade Commission, 1936
      Address by FTC Commissioner Ewin L. Davis - The Federal Trade Commission and Its Relation to Agriculture.
    - Federal Works Agency, 1941-1944 (Folder 69)
      Lists of approved FWA projects for North Carolina; information on miscellaneous FWA projects which do not have separate folders.
    - Federated Cooperative Exchange, 1936, 1939 (Folder 70)
    - Fertilizer, 1947
      Material concerns a shortage of nitrogen used in making fertilizer.
    - Fire Control Project, 1935-1936
    - First Citizens Bank, 1935
      Correspondence concerning efforts to establish branches in Rose Hill and Vanceboro through the Reconstruction Finance Corporation.
    - Fish and Fisheries, 1941-1960 (Folder 71-72)
      Correspondence related to Federal and state policies on the stocking of ponds through governmental assistance, the menhaden fishing industry, Pivers Island Federal Research Laboratory and the marine exhibit at Morehead City.
    - Flags, 1955-1956 (Folder 73)
    - Flood Insurance Program, 1957
      Correspondence concerns how North Carolina can meet the qualifications for the Federal Flood Insurance Program.
    - Fluoridation of Water, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 74)
      Correspondence focuses on pros and cons of fluoridation; also 17 pamphlets from the American Dental Association and the American Medical Association in favor of fluoridation.
    - Forest Service, U. S. and N. C. ca. 1944-1959 (Folder 75)
    - Fort Macon State Park Project, 1940
    - Fremont Community Building Project, 1936
    - Fremont School Project, 1940
    - Gasoline 1941-1945 (Folder 76-79)
      Bulk of correspondence deals with rationing of gasoline and Barden's efforts to assist his constituents.
    - General Accounting Office, 1953-1954 (Folder 79)
      Includes several bulletins from Lindsay Warren, Comptroller General and former Congressman from N. C.
    - G. I. Bill, 1944-1952 (Box 14, Folder 80)
      Correspondence deals with attempts by GI's to get loans, problems with lending institutions and the Veterans Administration June-July, 1951 - several letters concern drinking at a Veteran Colored School.
    - Glovers Creek Project, 1937see also Cedar Creek Project.
    - Goldsboro, Town of [1956?] (Folder 81)
      3 pamphlets: Goldsboro, Welcome to Goldsboro, North Carolina, and Seymour Johnson Air Force Base, and Goldsboro, Wayne County, North Carolina, Industrial Survey.
    - Goldsboro Airport Project, 1940-1942
    - Goldsboro Fire Station Project, 1938 (Folder 82)
    - Goldsboro Health Center, 1947
      Correspondence deals with the sale of the Health Center building by the Federal Works Agency to Wayne County.
    - Goldsboro Hospital Project, 1941-1944, 1956
      Correspondence concerns needed expansion of the hospital because of its use by persons associated with Seymour Johnson Air Base.
    - Goldsboro Municipal Golf Course, 1955 (Folder 83)
    - Goldsboro Post Office, 1948
    - Goldsboro Water and Sewer Project, 1938
    - Goshen Swamp Drainage Project, 1939
    - Grain Storage, 1951
      Correspondence focuses on a proposal to build a Cooperative Grain Storage Facility at Faison, N.C
    - Grave Marking Project for Veterans, 1939 - Correspondence concerns efforts to obtain Works Progress Administration funds
    - Halls School Teacherage Project, 1938-1939
    - Harkers Island Athletic Field Project, 1935-1936
    - Harkers Island Harbor Project 1940
    - Harkers Island Rural Electrification Administration Project, 1936-1939, 1941
    - Havelock, Town of 1959
      Correspondence deals with the acquisition of a government building to be used as the Havelock town hall
    - Health, Education and Welfare, Department of, 1954-1957
      Includes information on seamen's benefits through the Public Health Service and 1956 statistics on Old Age and Survivor's Insurance by state or by county in North Carolina.
    - Henderson Textile Workers Strike, 1959 (Folder 84)
      Bulk of material consists of clippings on the strike from N. C. newspapers: also copies of letters to Governor Hodges protesting use of National Guard, his reply and related statements: and several letters from the Textile Workers Union of America.
    - Highway Program, 1959-1960 (Folder 85)
    - Hobucken Bridge Project, 1937-1939
    - Hobucken School Project, 1940-1941
    - Holly Ridge School Project, 1947
      Correspondence concerns the purchase of the old Holly Ridge School building by the Holly Ridge Baptist Church.
    - Holly Ridge Water and Sewer Project, 1941, 1946-1947
    - Holly Shelter Canal Project, 1951
    - Holly Shelter Creek Project, undated
    - Home Owners Loan Corporation, 1935-1939 (Folder 85)
    - (Box 15, Folder 86)
      Correspondence revolves around Barden's attempts to assist constituents obtain loans from HOLC.